The questions that you asked the agent
is going to affect the quality of the
thing that you get out.
>> This is Michael Bolin, tech lead for the
open source Codex repository and former
distinguished engineer at Meta, and we
talked about how his career grew.
>> So it was like, all right, hackathon,
totally going to like make a new build
system, you know, like relatively
quickly have something that was
dramatically better, like at least like
twice as fast.
>> He shared about how OpenAI engineers
actually [music] use Codex.
>> I almost feel a little bad writing code
by hand.
>> What percent of your code would you say
is human written?
>> Yeah, cuz every time I sit down, I'm
like, should I write this? I mean, the
answer is almost always no.
>> And we discussed AI research versus big
tech engineering cultures.
>> What are your thoughts on that
research-led culture versus
engineering-led culture?
>> I mean, it's certainly an adjustment,
right? I'm not I mean, I think anyone
who comes here and says otherwise is a
liar.
>> [laughter]
>> Here's the full episode.
I was looking deep into your website,
and there was something most everything
I could find more information about, but
there's this one thing that you seem to
be pretty excited about at the time that
I couldn't find any information about it
cuz all the links were dead. What is
chickenfoot?
>> Oh man, that's strangely relevant
because it's uh it was my my master's
thesis project.
Uh it was a Firefox extension.
Uh probably one of the very few that was
written, you know, in JavaScript for
Firefox as a thesis project. And it was
uh it was actually a little coding tool
in a sidebar Firefox. And it was like a
little uh repple. It was called end-user
Yeah, the idea was end-user programming
for the web. And so there were functions
like enter and click and things like
that. And you'd say enter and you know,
to have pass a string arg and it would
like find the box and you'd say click
search or whatever. And um and you know,
a lot of the work was all these
heuristics that we built under the hood
that if you said, you know, enter first
name, finding the like the words first
and name and finding the text box that
was closest and then like using that and
then through JavaScript like
using that as the input. And I just
think about that now because it's really
funny we did all you know a lot of work
and that's
you know a lot of what these agents are
doing right now, right? It's like
similar. But now actually truly in
natural language like not in this little
like JavaScript repple.
>> Uh interesting. So it parsed the front
end and had this repple where you could
say I don't know, find the the first
name field and you know
>> Yeah, we'd use like the you know the the
accessibility tags and alt alt text for
images and we'd you know how and and it
worked well. Um
it was really good at Craigslist
actually cuz that's one of the simplest
uh
websites you could you could use. But I
had I had friends who like made like
automated tasks and like made real money
off of things they automated with this
tool. It's which is really fun.
>> When you entered the industry, you were
really excited about going to Google and
specifically working on Google Calendar.
>> Yeah.
>> Um so what drew you to Google and what
was that like?
>> Yeah, I mean you know, so I you know got
online in the '90s, right? And I
remember you know browsing the web and
it was at a time you'd go to like you'd
try five different search engines to
like hopefully find the thing that you
wanted. And I and I it's funny cuz I
distinctly remember my roommate in March
of 2000 saying like hey, there's this
site this search engine that looks a
little bit better. I think it was still
stanford.google.edu.
And I was like oh this is better and
like you know, and then
you started reading and they they were
just so different, right? Yahoo was all
like very cluttered and like they tried
to be very sparse and um were more I
think principled about it at that time.
And then
you know like a lot of things you start
seeing people who you know who gets a
job there and you're like oh man they're
they're taking really good people like I
want to work with
with those people and I felt like they
just
you know really got the web like
especially at that time when like
Microsoft didn't around that time
Microsoft killed the Internet Explorer
project altogether and I was like this
is the portal into the web and you guys
are you know, dismantling it. Whereas,
you know, Google was way more, you know,
web forward. And so, between that and
like the quality of engineering and the
and the impact they were having, you
know, certainly a place that I was
really excited to go to coming out of
school.
>> And what was the culture like there at
the time? Like um I think in some of
your writing you talked about like
products versus infrastructure.
>> You know, a lot of companies, especially
ones that get big like that, you know,
it's kind of like whatever they're good
at first is
I feel like the founders always have a
have a soft spot uh for, right? So, uh
certainly infor- information retrieval
and and infrastructure, right? Were like
key to, you know, growing that that
company. And um
whereas I
was drawn there at the time cuz like,
you know, they put out things like
Gmail, right? Which which were big,
right? But it didn't um
it still I think didn't have the the
same cachet inside the company, right?
As the as search and that sort of thing.
Um and so, you know, wait, when I was
working on it, calendar it was still
like mostly consumer, right? It was like
kind of
it was also sold to enterprises, right?
But like we were not the ones making the
money. Like we were probably a cost
center, right? Uh at that point in time.
>> I saw eventually you you ended up
leaving Google and I mean from your post
it looks like it was pretty bittersweet.
So, what led you to leaving Google?
>> I'd been there for 4 years. Um and you
know,
uh I mean realistically like investing
was a
>> [laughter]
>> like finances definitely changed after
that 4-year period uh ended. But you
know, also it was just tough. Like I I
had a I guess a bad habit at that point
of working really hard on things that
like really were important to me, but
maybe weren't important to to Google,
right? So, like I worked on calendar.
That was pretty important. Um and then I
worked on Google Tasks, which was like a
very small feature within calendar,
right? Like probably at least two to
three orders of magnitude fewer users,
right? But I was really passionate about
it. And then I was really passionate
about um um
the like the JavaScript infra and the
the the closure that that suite of uh
JavaScript tools.
And um you know, it's great. I mean, I
enjoyed and I'm proud of all the effort
that I put into the things
um you know, that I went and wrote the
the book on closure cuz I was so
motivated, but uh career-wise, maybe not
the best move, right? You're like, "Oh,
but I'm doing all this high-quality
stuff." And you see other people getting
recognized. You're like, "But I'm
working so hard, you know." Like that's
you know, kind of like the the harder
not smarter uh type of mistake. Um and
so [clears throat]
you know, it's kind of like I should go
somewhere
or try something else and see if like
the things that I'm excited about are
the things that like the company I'm
working at is most excited about.
>> Later, you came back into big tech and
you you started working at Facebook. I
understand that you were kind of like a
JavaScript expert at the time and then
one of your first big projects at uh
Meta was kind of build tooling in the
Android code base. So, I want to know
the story behind how you got involved in
in that.
>> So, um at the time, it was like
Facebook's going to make a phone, right?
Actually, there were some failed
projects, but it was like this time it's
really going to happen. We're going to
um partner with HTC. We're going to like
fork Android and you know, and and do
some stuff. And uh you know, so that
seemed uh
super exciting, right? Uh as a as a
person, you know, just coming into the
company. And and I you know, I done like
quite a bit of Java. I was more
JavaScript. Um
but
uh
at this point, this is also where
you know, they called it what uh
Faceweb, the version of like they kind
of like put HTML5 Facebook on the phone.
And like that was clearly not working
and
um
it was clear that like you know, mobile
was going to be the future. That was
kind of make or break for the company.
And uh suddenly
you know, a friend was like, "Hey, like
I know you really like Java Script, but
like you should really pick Java or
Objective-C and like get good at this if
you want to be a product person." And
that was really really great advice. And
so I was like, "Well, I like Java. I
don't like Objective-C, so like let's
go."
Um
and so that's how I, you know, found
myself on that project. Um and I
you know, we we had a very short
timeline because unlike almost every
other project, there was a hard
deadline. Usually, you know, you ship
when it's ready. This was like, "Nope,
we got to send a bill to HTC cuz they're
going to like burn it into phones on
like March 1st or whatever it was."
Um
so, you know, it was really a scramble.
Um but
and
the the original Android code base was
or a bunch of it was also like inherited
from a contractor that Google paid. Like
it's like Facebook didn't want to make
like a native app and they paid some
guy, and then it was like the app in the
store and they're like, "Here, the
code's yours now." And we should have
thrown it away, but we didn't. And so
there were a lot of things that were
that were frustrating, but also like
iteration time, right? I think for
everybody, if you'd been a web developer
for such a long time, you're used to
this edit refresh,
and then, you know, it like the Android
build system was was rough, right? It
was just
some build tools and Ant, and it like
there were no There was no way to
modularize it out of the box. Like we
had to hack it up just to even have like
four modules or five modules or
something like that. Um
and it was so
painful to get anything done
uh that I was like, "I need to I need to
fix the build system." And I was like,
"I know, I've done a lot with Java. I
know it's not like fundamentally this
slow to like iteratively, you know,
build this sort of thing."
And so,
uh you know, Facebook has this hackathon
culture. So, I was like, all right,
hackathon, totally going to like make a
new build system. Um you know, like
unceremoniously in the style of of
Google's build system. Um and there was
actually another build system called
FBBuild that was already a different
uh mirror of of the Google build system
as well.
Uh that one was written in in Python and
only did C++ but um
Yeah, and I was like either I'm going to
make this work or and like and I'm then
I'm going to be happy to be a developer
or like I don't even know if I'm going
to
make it here cuz it's just going to be
like tearing my hair out, you know,
working on this thing.
And uh
>> Let's say if you if you didn't fix this,
you would have quit the company if
>> Well, I
It was I mean, it was I was like or I'll
at least switch projects or something. I
need to find a way to find a happy
place, right? And and come in work every
day. Like I came, I want to write code,
I want to do work. I just want to
you know, try to do my best work. Um and
so it was funny actually they give
people credit. A lot of people
told me what I was doing was a very bad
idea.
Um almost everybody except one person.
Um
I was a senior Android engineer.
Uh but nobody said no, you know, whereas
I felt like at Google like people said
no more. Um and so
uh so I just rolled with it and you
know, I quickly relatively quickly had
something that was
you know, dramatically better. Like at
least like twice as fast or something
like that. And uh so that, you know, it
turned a lot of heads and people were
like
okay, you know,
>> [laughter]
>> I guess we we'll go with that one,
right? Like
>> I think the interesting thing to me is
it seemed like all the odds were
stacking against you. A lot of people
who are engineers notice the same
problem would not have chosen to
start the project because there's an
existing one and then also Google's got
some, you know, competing one. Maybe
you're not going to beat that one. What
gave you the conviction that your
your project could beat the other ones
and become the default?
>> Yeah, I mean, I guess a couple things. I
mean, one like I said, I you know, I'd
done other Java stuff. I was like like
this shouldn't be that slow. Or just as
a software engineer, like this
fundamentally should not be as slow um
as it is. And
there were yeah, most of the actually
most of the pushback was of the nature
like, well, if we deviate from the
standard thing,
um you know, we're not going to be on
the standard thing. And what if it gets
like 100x better next week and now we're
stuck on your thing. Um which is really
funny when you think about it because
there's like so many things like, you
know, making their own, you know,
uh
PHP virtual machine and language, right?
Like they've certainly embraced doing
their own thing many times. Why this one
was different? I don't know. I mean, it
was it was just I guess everything about
mobile was like, how are you going to
make this work? I guess there was just
like a lot of
fear and you know, again, like
timelines. It's like we have the senior
person, like why? It seems like sounds
like they're going to go off and do a
side or scratch project. But we have a
hard deadline. Like is that the best use
of our
of our time? Um
but you know, it it worked out. It
worked out. Uh I will say another thing,
too,
was um
I also tried to
to couch it a little bit. I was like,
"Hey, I'm just I'm just trying to make
an Android build system. I'm not trying
to like take over the company. I'm not
trying to change anyone else's project,
right?" Um because I certainly felt that
that was going to cause more I was going
to just fight more friction. Um and so,
you know, I
I knew that it it I tried to make it in
a way that it could support more of the
company, but I never I never pushed it.
And so, I was like really heartened when
the
year or so later, the iOS people were
like,
"Hey, our build system sucks. [laughter]
Can we You know, can we use Buck?" I was
like, "Yeah, sure. Like I don't, you
know,
come on board."
>> Yeah, that that's also another
interesting cuz you you came in and you
didn't have a whole lot of credibility.
You were just hired.
>> Yeah.
>> And then you're trying to build
something and get every And also
everyone's saying, "Don't."
>> Yes.
>> And then you have to convince them,
"Hey, this is the right direction."
How'd you influence that change without
any credibility?
>> I I mean, I borrowed some. Um there's
one senior Android engineer, you know,
who's also ex-Google, um
uh John Perlow, and he was like I think
he said, right? He's like, "You're going
to do it, just do it fast before like
anyone gets, you know, the cancer or
something." He's like, "Well, I'll
support you if you
if you get this done." So, he was one of
the first people and he was a very
prolific uh coder. So, he was like
genuinely very happy to have a faster
dev cycle. Um so, he was one of the
first people to, you know, give it kudos
and I think that that helped a lot. Um
also, but I will say, you know, I
I made a a big some big mistakes uh on
my way in there. You you know, you
mentioned like about having no
credibility. It's like, you know, I came
from Google
and I was like, "Oh, this is where, you
know, the ex-Bell Labs people are, like
all these like great people." And then
you go to like Facebook and you're like,
"Oh, it's a bunch of college kids. How
could they possibly know what they're
doing?" Right? And you you know, I made
a few times, certainly, I made the
mistake like, "Well, at Google, we did
it this way." And people are like, "We
really don't care." You know, and they
were and they were right in in in most
cases, right? That like just because it
worked there didn't mean it was going to
work here.
>> One one last thing on this topic is
I mean, what you built was
way more performant than anything else
by, you know, well, many multiples.
What's the intuition, like the technical
intuition behind what was done and what
you did that made it so much more
efficient?
>> I think the the big thing was is that I
just sat down and looked at the um the
tool from Google and I was like, "What
is it actually doing?" Right? And and
where and uh I I the big thing is that
the Google one
would kind of just if you changed
anything it would just start over from
scratch. And so that's why it was so
slow especially for for incremental
builds. And so then I started to really
understanding like okay but what depends
on what cuz there is these there's still
are sure like Android resources which
had like a very bespoke thing and it was
it was complicated. Um
and because it was somewhat complicated
I think that's probably why it just by
default it blew everything away and
started over. Um but once I got in there
and I was like oh okay you know we can
take advantage of it these things don't
change then you know we can cache this
result from this step we don't have to
redo it and like suddenly you know that
made things like quite a bit faster and
then also just even
um
supporting the idea that you had of more
than like
the four modules that we had I mean I
think I think every time someone added a
module you know they had to add like 200
lines of XML of like ant build script
that like nobody really understood and
so it was not so no one no no one wanted
to modularize anything right you didn't
want to be responsible for that so big
thing with Buck was making it that it
was like a lot um
simpler to add a new module and so then
that also meant we ended up with more
modules and then builds are more
incremental as a result right so it's
really a change in the
the mindset.
>> So less redundant work basically.
>> Yeah.
>> After you solved this build problems I
guess in Android builds and I obviously
went later to further parts of the
company
I saw that you started to work more on
like the IDE. What was the problem that
you saw that you saw in IDEs that make
you want to get into that?
>> So I yeah I took I did a brief stint
after Buck on Messenger.
Uh I iOS Messenger so I was like okay
I've done Android maybe I should
actually branch out even though I don't
like it. Um and I still didn't like it.
Um I
people don't even realize in in in in
Objective-C there's a thing that happens
for a long time now called ARC um
like the automatic, uh, reference
counting. Like nowadays, the compiler
injects it, but you used to have to like
actually add code in Objective-C to do
every like reference count
>> Like explicitly allocation, right?
>> Yeah, or like every reference that you
created, like you would have to do it.
And, um, and the
And and most people have never seen this
type of code, but the iOS Messenger code
that came in through acquisition was so
old that it was still written in this
other way, and it's it's it's incredibly
painful.
Um, I guess now you'd have to like Codex
cleaned it up or something. Yeah, but at
the time we just sucked it up. And and
and just Xcode just didn't, you know,
feel right to me. I didn't like header
files and implementation files. I still
don't. Um,
and it also the I would say
for both Android and iOS, you know,
Facebook always had like the biggest
app, right? We had like one app
with every with every feature in it, and
we, you know, we'd ship it, as opposed
to Google with like they'd have like a
Drive app and a no you know, a Sheets
app or whatever, but they also owned one
of the platforms, so they could put 20
apps by default on there.
And so what that meant was is that
Facebook was always hitting the the
scaling limits of every mobile developer
tool before everybody else,
um, which was painful, but, you know,
actually as a dev tools person, it was
kind of interesting cuz we got to solve
problems that nobody had solved before.
Um, and like and like, you know, not
just as a science project, but because
it was like real, you know, business
value. Um, and so,
you know, Xcode, similarly, we we talked
to Apple, we were like, "Hey, Xcode's
like not really scaling to our project."
They're like, "Your project's too big.
You should make it smaller." Like that
was kind [laughter] of the feedback that
we got from them. And so it seemed
justifiable to like go and build an
another It was similar thing. It was
like I was like, "What is, you know,
what is an IDE
you know, doing, right?" It's like it's
talking to clang, like the language
server, that sort of stuff. I was like,
"We can build like a nicer shell on top
of that." You know, and then we had
started by that point um,
deviating from Git and switching to
Mercurial as a company. I was like, "No
one's going to support Mercurial out of
the box, right?" And so, like, that
should happen. And then, like, "Oh,
actually, if if Buck is going to be our
build system, then like we really like,
you know, like that's Xcode's never
going to do all of these bespoke
Facebook things, right? So, it seemed
justifiable to like invest the time to
um to try to like improve that
experience. And I didn't feel that way
about Android cuz IntelliJ was actually
like quite good. And we had figured out
how to make that work at scale. But but
Xcode was a little more difficult at
that point.
>> So, there was Xcode, which was bad,
didn't fit the existing needs. And then
there was
another IDE that another team was
building. I think it was web-based if I
>> It was exactly It was web-based. Um
I'm not I don't like that part. That
That part's fine. It was But it was
built off of an abandoned Google
open-source project written in GWT,
which is Google Web Toolkit, where you
would write Java and it would code gen
to to JavaScript for everything.
And um I tried to build on what they
had. I tried to rebuild some
credibility. It even actually sped up
their build a bit.
Um
but again, kind of like looking at the
iteration times. And also, I was like,
"This is an abandoned open-source
project. It's written in Google Web
Toolkit." And I was like, "We are the
React company at that point, right?
Right? Like, how
Why why would we not empower,
you know, people who want to build dev
tools to use, you know, for
you know, to build on a
you know, technologies that we are the
leader in and actually really like
because, you know, we think we're
actually really good." Um
so,
I was like, "You guys are crazy." And
>> [laughter]
>> so I started I got And And then, similar
to the thing where I, you know, I
mentioned with the Buck, I was like, I
started it as the
the Java build tool, not the everything
build tool, right? I was like It was a
similar thing. I was like, "Hey, I'm
going to go over here and start this
other other but we're just we're just
going to focus on iOS. Like you I'm not
trying to take things over.
>> Yeah, you didn't want all the friction
and I mean, that team they had all the
existing users though, right? They had
thousands of engineers.
>> even maybe a thousand, I don't think.
>> Eventually leadership sided with
um what eventually became Nuclide, which
is what you what you built. Um but why
did they side with you when you didn't
have any users on your share platform?
>> Yeah, I mean, I think it was combination
of two things. I mean, I think the the
arguments that I made in favor of um
like the technology stack to build on.
Um another was that um
uh Nuclide was was a desktop application
and part of it was if this is actually
going to be a an iOS, you know, Xcode
replacement, like people are going to
want to use
need to be able to talk to the simulator
or plug in the phone or whatever. Like
in theory, we could go through the web
and do all those things, but it just
seems like a lot more a lot of extra
work.
Um
and um and I think the other part is
that, you know, I had built up some
credibility with the with the Buck thing
that um they're willing to like take a
gamble. They're like, "Well, the last
thing paid off. It worked out. Like why
don't we try this one?"
>> I saw that this, in combination with
some of your other work, led to your
promotion to E8, which is also known as
principal in the industry.
What was your reaction to that at the
time?
>> Yeah, I mean,
certainly I was I was very excited. Um
you know, I felt like you know, in the
ways that I
um had been out of step, I felt like,
you know, when I was at Google, I was
like, "This is also not just it was also
validation that like, "Oh, now I'm
also growing not just like technically,
but like understanding like what it
means to kind of, you know, do the
things that like are in line with your
uh employer." Um and so like that also
just, you know, was equally valuable or
satisfying.
>> I I know that uh Nuclide was open source
and I think Buck was as well if I recall
correctly. What's the rationale for open
sourcing if um Yeah, like what are the
pros and cons of open sourcing
technology that you build?
>> Yeah, I mean let's see the
Buck is the more interesting one.
Nuclide kind of didn't really get
adopted externally. I I think in both
cases I think
um
you know, all these companies have
benefited so much from open source. Like
there I think there's just a feeling of
like if it's not really the secret sauce
like
but let's share this with with other
people, right? Like I mean done and like
Codex as well and a number of other
things in my career. So I do feel like
that that that sharing of information is
just good. Even if no one uses your tool
just as like seeing as a reference of
like how a thing could be done um
could be great. Um you know, in in the
in the better scenarios you actually
get, you know, meaningful contributions
back and and things like that. And um
you know, I remember like I think Uber
adopted Buck. I think Airbnb did. Like
it was funny, right? Like I said like
Facebook was the biggest app so we would
hit all these problems first and then
this next wave of companies would start
hitting these things and be like, let's
check out what these guys did. Um I
think I mean honestly we also, you know,
at at at Google it was uh it's
internally it's Blaze, externally it's
Bazel. Uh so we were open source first
and we always did we always did kind of
want to like if we put some pressure on
like you know, we get and it ultimately
they did. I think I think I think we've
gotten a little bit of credit from that
unofficially from uh some of the folks
who worked on that. But I think also
that, you know, we you know, it's also
like a a recruiting thing too or just
showing like, hey if you want to like,
you know, being at like the you know,
the the leading edge in like whatever
area this technology is and you want to
do this all the time not just as like a
drive-by contributor, like you know,
this is what we do. This is who we are.
>> And then this decision to open source,
is this was this a bottoms-up decision
where engineers said we're just going to
do this or is this kind of
also leadership buy-in, hey, this is
going to be valuable and you got like a
doc.
>> Yeah. Yeah, I think
I think both cases it was certainly like
bottoms-up. I don't think
So, you know, things like React and
PyTorch, like those are like the the big
success stories, right? Where where the
value back to the company is like
unquestionable. And then there's this
like longer tail
of things where
I think depending on the economy and
other things the managers get grumpy if
they feel like our engineers are like
doing too much open source or things
like that. So, it's almost almost always
I feel like like bottoms-up. I think
yeah, I would say that's that's often
the case. But it wasn't like met with a
lot of resistance, you know, and you
usually get like
like a good conference talk or two and a
nice blog post. And And those blog posts
like, you know, do I would say they pay
dividends over time.
>> Right. Like trying recruiting
>> Yeah, like they have like a like a
longer shelf life than I think people
realize.
>> Okay, so you got your your E8 promo at
this point and I imagine the
expectations maybe in your mind are kind
of going up a little bit and now you
need to go and find a E8 problem, I
guess.
>> Yeah.
>> So, what did you do after you got
promoted?
>> Uh I think that's where I did a
I I
got a little over my skis and I tried to
help with web speed, I think is what I
did. Um cuz again, it was a thing that
was like a really big problem for the
like like the just the load time of
facebook.com was was not in great shape.
Um you know, the architecture was a bit
stale.
Um and it was just um
the problem was so big
and um
and I didn't have
I think the you know, a lot of people
who had worked on web at Facebook had
worked on it for like a long time. And
like I had you know put myself in mobile
and dev tools I actually wasn't
in that world and um
I remember I was like you know what do
we do I mean actually sit down with the
other person we started like compiling
V8 from source and try to see like if we
could like change the way that we
generated JavaScript if it was like it'd
be friendlier to V8 like we're just
trying like wacky things none of which
panned out by the way and I just it was
it was
there's different there's different
people who are like good for different
projects and I think that was just not
the one like I'm better in a project
that involves writing a lot of code from
the beginning
and I think a project like that was like
more about like looking at data and
talking to a lot of people and like I
just that's not my strength
>> I think you mentioned that at this point
in your career the the idea of a hero
quest
what's what's that mean
>> the idea that you know that uh
>> [sighs]
>> it's like you know it's embarrassing cuz
there's like some amount of ego
idea that you know there's this like you
know Gordian knot and all these
engineers are like
if only someone would come in and like
solve this you know engineering problem
I was like I know JavaScript right I
thought I was like okay
just come in that way and uh
but I didn't I did I definitely did not
you know
uh and I think that um it's been an
important learning and I had to relearn
it like at least one other time that
you know
I can do a lot of things but there
there's a smaller subset of things that
I really genuinely enjoy doing and that
I'm going to be a lot more successful
right if I stay in the things that I
genuinely enjoy doing and you know I try
to expand that over time but
you know we don't all have to be the
best at everything right I think that's
we should accept it and
you know embrace it
>> so then how did you find the EA problem
after that like what was the next step
are you
>> that was
uh I think a bit of luck as well all
right, I guess you know, we had we had
sometimes we'd have these little
summits
with like smaller groups of engineers
about like brainstorming what's going to
you know, bite us in the future. Yeah, I
mentioned I was like, you know, the repo
keeps growing.
You know, we're you know, we're going to
have some scaling problem at some point
and um
yeah, a person or my manager, then he
became a manager, Brian O'Sullivan,
um
he decided to get some people together
to like work on making a virtual file
system
to
do get try to get ahead of that that
problem. Um and so we got myself and
Adam Simpkins and Wes Furrlong, you
know, both
tremendous engineers. Actually, I
thought I was the worst engineer on the
tech for quite a bit.
>> You mentioned a virtual file system.
What on a high level what's the benefit
to a company like uh Meta for if you had
something like that?
>> If you
have bought into the mono repo
philosophy, right? Put all the code in
one repo. Um
you know, most things that people do
need only a subset of that repo like
they have to look at the the files at
any point in time.
And um
so the idea is that
you know, you design all your tooling
around this virtual file system so that
when you say clone the repo or then you
update to a different commit or anything
like that, you don't actually have to
like write out every single file in the
repo on disk when you make that change,
which is which is the default in your
you know, traditional file system
because that um is going to grow
proportionally to the time with the the
size of the repo, right? So at some
point you're you know, going to be very
sad. And um
and
and so, you know, there's actually kind
of two
at least two parts to it. One is
um building this virtual file system
that's like, hey, I know the user got
this commit. If if the operating system
asked me for the contents of a file,
like I can go get it and it will appear
like they had actually, you know, laid
out all the files. Um the other part of
it, which is the part that I maybe I was
actually better at, I think, is um
then try to anticipate to say, well, we
have all these tools in our tool chain
that are used to just reading all the
files. You know, you just rip grab it
just reads everything, right? That sort
of thing. And how do we start changing
also our our development flow and our
tools such that they are um uh designed
with the virtual file system in mind
because if you just, you know,
materialize all the files with your tool
and they've like actually just lost all
your the benefits that that you've made.
>> So, on a high level, it's basically just
lazy loading a huge file system. So,
it's more efficient cuz you don't need
to do everything at the beginning.
>> Yeah.
>> And so, that part of this project that
you said you're better at is is
integrating everything into this on top
of that primitive.
>> Yeah. Yeah, so one thing that I did um
actually with uh Hanson Wong who's here
actually I'm on the Codex team with me
now. Um was I was like, okay, you know,
the the traditional way you have, you
know, you want um really fast file
search in your in your IDE and your
editor. And you know, the way most of
these things do is the first thing they
do is they walk the entire file system
to find out what the files are. And I
was like, well, that's going to be a
that's going to be a serious problem,
right? It's going to undo all the
benefits like and and then it's one of
these things is like not, you know,
first it was like, okay, how can we
implement file search that's not going
to undo all the benefits? And then it
was how can we do it
even better than
>> what's done uh today.
>> And so, we ended up um building this
file system called Miles, short for my
files. And it um you know, on like kind
of like a cron job, it would index um it
it would ingest all the new commits that
had come in on, you know, on trunk and
keep track of like which files had been
added or removed. So, just like the
names of the files, not the contents,
cuz all you need is the names.
And um
and then and then uh Hanson had some
clever ideas about how we maintained
that index
um such that we could support fuzzy file
matching. So, instead of just substring
matching, right? Like you type, you
know, like a if you have like a camel
case thing, you want to be able to type
just maybe the uppercase letters or just
your spellings better, what have you.
Um
and so it came up with this really uh
interesting way to represent uh you
know, kind of all the files that had
been seen at some point and then some
bits to represent um you know, if I'm at
this commit was this file present or not
present at that point in time. And then
also
when you ask when you send a query to
this thing, so you'd send like what
commit you're at and like if you've
added any files locally or removed any
locally. Um
and I think we got this, you know, like
you know, over a million files in like
I don't know, like 10 to 20 milliseconds
or something like that. So, that you
would be in your editor, you know,
typing. And so that was way faster than
uh I think than, you know, like what
Xcode or or like even VS Code or
something like would give you
um out of the box. And um so so that
was, you know, so like it was solving a
problem for
Eden, that that was the name of the file
system originally, the virtual file
system. Um
you know, in anticipation and before it
was even ready. Um but then it was so
fast um and it was available as a thrift
service internally, like people started
using it for all sorts of other things.
I think when I left, like
I don't know, I think there were at
least like 30 servers running models
like spread around the globe.
>> [laughter]
>> So, clearly that was more than just
people like personally searching for
files if they needed that much, you
know, capacity.
>> Interesting. Yeah, I mean, when you
talked about, I guess, the
implementation details
most most people they they don't use
LeetCode on the job. But
that sounds like I'm just thinking about
the I don't I don't even know how you
input that. Is it like a tree like a
trie thing?
>> No, that So, that's what's funny that
trie Yeah, um this was this was pretty
cool and that
we
we had kind of like two parallel arrays.
One was like the file contents
and one was maybe an integer into that
um
index. I forget. And then we had a we
had a 64-bit
um
uh
mask that was like it was like so you
had like
26 lowercase, 26 capital, 10 digits and
like maybe dash and whatever.
>> Yeah.
>> And and it would and it was a every bit
was set if the
um
if that character was used at all in the
file that you were searching. And so the
first thing was we could like blow
through that list
and um you know, exclude a bunch of
things like right off the top. But we
had also like very designed like all
these arrays were in parallel to each
other so that
for like cache-wise, we knew it'd be
very efficient for for the CPU to to
like read memory, you know, linearly.
And then it it lent itself to you could
just partition that array. It you know,
lent itself to parallelism.
>> Mhm.
>> Um So, it's really Yeah, I should really
probably write it up at some point.
>> That's
>> That is really cool. It was It was fun
because it wasn't just kind of like out
of the textbook. That's that's for sure.
>> I understand that um yeah, you worked on
Eden and then obviously this Miles as
well.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and then these eventually led to
another promotion and um but prior to
that promotion, there was
learnings you might have had about
influence and conflict in orgs. Maybe
you can share that.
>> Yeah, I mean that's
One of the things I guess about being an
E8 um who primarily writes
code, right? Um there's other people
I'd say actually the majority of people
that level or higher are not writing
code, right? They're they're actually
kind of exclusively spent
doing more like influence or working
across teams, you know, writing the big
Google Doc and getting everyone on board
and all that
sort of stuff. And so, you know,
as an E8 trying to have that level like,
you know, that level of impact that
you're expected to have, it's like, oh,
it's hard to do that just writing code.
So, it's like I need to spend at least
some time
probably probably influencing other
people. That would probably be be good
for me. That would probably make my
manager happy.
Um
And
I think
uh
you know, sometimes you're just so
uh confident in in some
insights you have that or certainly I
was that I would just I I just came down
like way too hard, I would say. And uh
and that did not go well for me.
And yeah, and so like like uh promo got
delayed because I was very excited or
anxious about uh when
Microsoft acquired GitHub.
And uh oh yeah, cuz the new client was
built on this um you know, primarily
GitHub technology. And I was like,
that's going to go away cuz VS Code's
going to not make them be a project
anymore, which was true, which did
happen.
And I was just so
uh anxious that that this was like now
at risk, right? And I was pushing
people, but you know, people were
I didn't really account for the fact uh
that people were happy with what they're
doing at the moment and like didn't want
their cheese moved, you know, like uh
right out from under them. And so, um
you know, I got like a little bit of a
talking to. I you know, I had to wait a
little bit for promo and things like
that. But I I you know, I actually
didn't get some coaching, I think, after
that point. I can't remember the exact
terminology, um
to to work on that like specifically.
What's the number one thing you learned
about coaching? I would say
for me is like um I think I'm more aware
of like things that trigger me. Like you
know, me or technical decisions or what
have you and recognize when that's
happening and be like, okay, let's not
act in that moment or
you know, if I if I don't think I can
have the conversation like uh or I'm not
the
in the best place to have it. Like maybe
I go talk to the person's manager
instead rather than like you know, like
bull in a china shop to the engineer and
be like
So, I have this thing. I'm thinking
about it this way. I'm kind of riled up
about it. Like how like how can I you
know, work with your team or whatever.
Like that's happened to you.
>> Well, it's interesting to me in your
career because
uh the promo got postponed and you were
you were seeing that VS code was going
to come up and the thing that New Cloud
was built on was going to go down.
And you were actually right in
hindsight, too. Like in the future, that
is what happened. And
you were battling for what was right.
Yet you were told
calm down a little bit and this stuff.
So, I mean what are your thoughts when
you saw things play out? You go,
actually I was right the whole time.
>> Um
I did have some conversations like about
a year later and I was like, hey.
>> [laughter]
>> Could we balance the ledger a little
bit? Like you didn't be pretty hard for
that thing and it was kind of good and
we we worked it out.
>> Yeah, I would say.
Okay, so I guess that the learning is
just
how you went about it, not what you were
like
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um
I would say that's true.
>> You seemed to have a great time at Meta
and eventually you left. So, what was
the thing that drew you to OpenAI?
>> Yeah, I mean um
a number of things. I mean one was uh so
I I interviewed at the end of 2023 with
OpenAI, I believe. And um and I'd spent
2023 at Meta um trying to do LLM based
developer tools, right? With uh there's
a, you know, we had our own like that
emergence in Meta made this like little
version of
GitHub Copilot, right? That one did like
a paper and a talk on that one. It was a
code compose, right? That was code
compose, yeah.
And, um, you know, we,
like now, uh,
there's a lot of, uh,
uh, enthusiasm around, you know,
delivering quickly and pushing the
boundaries of that sort of stuff. And,
uh,
you know,
I mean, truth of it, I mean, you know,
you get feedback on some of these
things. It's like, "Hey, why is this
not, you know, GPT-4?" And I was like,
"Well, we're on like Lambda 2. It's not
the same thing." And, uh, you know, I
was not not a researcher, right? I was
like, "I but I and I, you know, just
wanted to to build the experiences,
right?" And that sort of thing. And, um,
and
so so that was that was one thing was
that like I wanted to build stuff and I
wanted to go to the place where I could
actually build with the best model. Um,
you know, two again was, um, similar to
like, you know, Google originally, like
seeing the people who were coming here
to OpenAI. And I was like, "Well, these
are people I really respect." I was
like, "Those are I can actually work
with more senior people,
you know,
like Meta eights and nines at OpenAI I
felt like that I could where I was." Um,
and, um,
you know,
third was just like this also seems
like, uh, and it has been just a very
special place at
at the point in time. So, I told a lot
of people I was like, you know, I felt
like this would be
like the most similar to starting at
Google in 2000. So, not like not to
1998, but like let's say 2000, right?
Like they kind of got some footing and
got some, you know, product market fit.
And so, like just as a personal level,
that was just a very exciting thing.
Um,
and, um, you know, and the last one was
that, uh, funny thing is that
when I I really enjoyed calendar cuz I
it was consumer and I shipped to lot of
people. I went to Facebook cuz I thought
huge consumer place. Ended up not doing
consumer at all, right? Ended up doing
developer tools, but like you know, my
users were my friends at work. It was
just like 20,000 people, not like a
billion people, but it was good enough
for me at the time. And then, you know,
thinking about open AI and then the
chance to actually, you know, come back
to to consumer um or at least like have
a large user base, right? And so now
working on Codex um
you know, I would have like over a
million weeklies or I forget how much it
is right now. Um and and just keeps
growing like like a little you know,
hockey stick or more like vertical line
than hockey stick even. Um that uh you
know, so it's like way more than the
20 to 40,000 developers, you know, I
guess that at meta.
>> Yeah, absolutely. And dev tooling for
the industry almost.
>> Yeah.
>> Um meta, when I think of the company,
it's kind of engineering driven. Like
engineers are king and queen, I guess.
And they kind of like drive everything.
It's very bottoms-up from that sense.
And I feel like a lot of the lab
companies
are also like that, but on the research
side. So, rather than engineers the
first a class citizen, it's like, let's
make sure the research goes well. And
for good reason, right? Like that's also
part of why you came is the models are
good.
>> Yep.
>> But as an engineer, uh you mentioned you
weren't doing uh research. Um what are
your thoughts on that research-led
culture versus engineering-led culture?
>> I mean, it was certainly an adjustment,
right? I'm not I mean, I think of anyone
who comes here and says otherwise is a
liar.
>> [laughter]
>> Um you know, if you've been at like the
FANGs or whatever. Um
and
uh but you know, they are
you know, you talk about impact, right?
Which I think is important. Like a real
like you genuinely, you know, mean it.
Um
like
I you know, I love the work that I do on
Codex and the harness and I think we do
a lot of very meaningful things.
Um but you know, if the model weren't
very good, it wouldn't really matter
what we did, you know, on the RNs,
right? And so, um, so I don't uh
So, you know, that that's how it is, I
would say.
Um, but I, you know, I I feel really
great like, you know, we we sit right
next to the the research team. Uh, we
work really closely with them.
Um, and so that relationship that we
have, that we get to
co-develop the thing. I mean, that that
was another reason, you know, leaving
leaving Meta, I mean, was that for for
for in the LM space was like,
you know, I want to build the product
with the people who are building the
model so that we can do this thing
together. I mean, you know, maybe you
could do that there sort of, but not
Anyway, the the the the the the the
impact was not, you know, quite quite
the same.
>> So, you mentioned, I mean, when you got
here, it sounds like you were working on
Codex and starting uh that project up.
So, I understand with the initial launch
of Codex CLI, it was uh not exactly what
you hoped for, like in terms of the how
it was received, but um later it kind of
really all came together. Can you tell
that story?
>> Yeah, sure. I mean,
it's been a wild ride. So, Codex CLI, we
launched it in April 2025. It was kind
of like this like one more thing moment
at the end of the O3 O4 mini uh live
stream.
And uh so, we demoed it live, we
open-sourced it, you know, got three
votes at point.
Uh, a lot of people tried it out, you
know, but everyone was excited to try a
new um
coding agent. You know, and it was and
it was pretty good, but it was it was
pretty rushed um to get it out the door,
right? There was um which in some ways
was good for engagement cuz now that
we're open source, we were getting pull
requests, you know, coming in all over
the place. And uh I forget, you know, we
were I feel like we're like 10 to 20,000
stars in like a week or two or something
like that. So, like that that part was
fun. And um, you know, there were people
who did like it, but you know, it's like
nobody thinks it or anything like that.
But then um
but that
I I think we didn't we weren't maybe
quite staffed to like really drive that
the way that we needed to um
because you know, we're we're trying to
cover multiple things as a company and
so you know, just a month after that and
you know, a team of like seven engineers
and I forget how many researchers
launched um Codex
web or cloud at web um where you know,
you can use Codex in a container or you
could just
you know, kick off a new thing from your
phone which is super cool and um
and there that was like a more
well-staffed effort and I and I think
you know, that one is still the
I think the the long-term vision is is
correct but I think with a lot of this
stuff that we've seen
you know, you have to bring the the
users with you and and uh and I think
that one was just like a little bit
ahead of its of its time and people were
still actually more into the the local
um coding agents. And so we kind of you
know, we saw
you know, the like the the web product
like there's a big adoption initially
it wasn't you know, as sticky I would
say as we we had hoped um and then
through the summer you know, both
products still kept kept uh you know,
we're working on both um but then
somewhere that midsummer again like I
said it's like you know, this moment
like local agents are still
the I guess the stronger product market
fit but again I I still think it in the
limit personally right like uh you're
you're you're going to need more
machines than just your laptop to as a
place for agents to run and um
so we we shifted quite a bit um over the
summer. So we we brought more people
onto the Codex CLI. Yeah, fuse the key
things but bring more people on
you know, GPT-5 was uh going to come out
and that was looking really really good
and um
I think I was personally excited about
cuz I had prototyped it a couple times
before um was that in addition to the
CLI then we also had enough staffing, we
had also started working on
the VS Code extension. And you know, and
I felt actually very strongly that, you
know, the the the terminal is good for a
lot of things, but it has a lot of
limitations always. Just It's just like
you make a lot of compromises to make,
you know, a nice UI in the terminal,
whereas VS Code we didn't have to make
quite as many compromises. And um
so I think like August, I think it was a
crazy month. I think GPT-5 came out. I
think we we released our new refreshed
terminal UI. Also the GPT open source
model came out. We supported that
in the in the 2E as well. So that was
really cool that we had, you know, an
open weights model on the and open
harness.
And um and then later that month the VS
Code extension, you know, came out. And
so we were just like, you know, shipping
like like crazy. And um and that's
really where like that confluence of
things, I would say, um is where we
started to see the inflection point
that's brought us to like, you know, the
vertical growth that we're that we're at
today. Um and so that's, you know, uh
that's been really exciting. I mean,
you know, some of these things you can
you can go to the repo check for
yourself, right? And and and you know,
go check it out on on some of these
things. Um in terms of number of people,
uh number of commits, and all this sort
of thing. Um
and yeah, so it's it's it's been quite a
ride.
>> You mentioned the local versus the
remote version of these coding agents,
and it sounds like you have a lot of
conviction that the right long-term
direction is not the local versions.
It's remote and in the cloud. Why is
that?
>> Well, I think about I think that the
people who actually for whom it is
sticky now, and I think there'll be more
of it, is that you imagine if you
imagine you want to just automatically
um
you know, for the agent at every like
GitHub issue or linear task thing that
comes in or anything like that. I mean,
obviously, you know, there's
there's costs with those things, but or
you can it could be abused. But like,
you know, let's say for an internal
private repo, right? That you Yeah, want
to be able to just have it be a piece in
the any sort of automation pipeline,
right? And so, you can't
>> [laughter]
>> you know, have all that happening on
your on your laptop. And so, I guess I
mean, you know, as a as an individual, I
see maybe we'll still personally spend
more time with the local agent. But in
terms of
uh you know,
compute time of agents doing work,
right? I think getting that set up in
the cloud I think you know, a little bit
it's like a little more to get set up
right now, but once you have it, it's
it's quite nice.
>> I see. Okay, so you're not saying that
product, the local one, will change.
You're saying that like across the
industry, the compute that goes towards
agents, majority will be in the cloud
and
>> Yeah, I mean, even in um
I think maybe when the VS Code extension
first came out, you know, one of the
things was um the ability to take the
conversation that you were having and
like at a button have it like transfer
to the cloud if you're set up to do it.
Right? And um
So, I think that we'll continue to see
that where you maybe you're working on
something you want to throw it over
here. You're like bring it back, you
know, when it's done.
>> And Codex usage is
uh 5x since the beginning of the year
and over a million people are using it
now. I'm curious, has your AI workflow
changed a lot since you've uh you know,
started to use this newer version of
Codex?
>> Yeah, it has it has. Um I'm much bigger
user of the app now maybe than I thought
I would be. Um
I
uh
Yeah, like
for a while I was I was
uh very strongly in like our VS Code
extension. Like I need I want that
sidebar. I want all the code there next
to me. I feel like these things should
be, you know, together.
Um
I'm not a I'm not a person who doesn't
look at the code. I'm not a like a
I don't
For for projects that are like true
prototypes that are throwaway, like I
will actually not look at the code. It's
very freeing. I understand why people
are so excited about it. But, for the
code that goes into Codex itself, I'm
like, "No, I still need to look at this,
right? This is pretty important. This is
like what's going to, you know, affect
everybody else." Um but, you know, you
start to get a sense of
Okay, that I like I'm confident the
model's going to be able to do this, you
know, this this change and this sort of
thing. Like I, you know, I don't need to
to babysit it. I'm going to just like
write a lot in the front. And so, you
know, I have like four or five clones of
the Codex repo on my machine. And I I
have enjoyed in the Codex app, um
like the multitasking I just is is just
a lot easier cuz you know, you're just
kind of hanging out in one window. Um
and
you know, I try and it's
not the game exactly, but it's like, you
know, it's like how much throughput can
I get, right? In terms of how many balls
can I juggle in the air? Sometimes it
feels like, um it you know, it can it
can feel like a little hectic when
you're really trying to
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> context context switch, right?
>> But, at the same time, you're you're
like, I I'm getting a lot more done, you
know, and uh
and that
you know, it almost feels a little bad
writing code by hand sometimes cuz
you're like, I I could have if I had
asked this in the right way, I I you
know, it's like it's like when you
started it was like, "Oh, I'm just going
to change these three lines." And then
like, you know, 30 minutes later you're
like, "Oh, I kind of
>> [laughter]
>> You know, that you know, we all we all
like to type still, I think, and that
sort of thing.
>> What percent of your code would you say
is human written versus the model
generates these days?
>> Oh, man, it's
model's got to be like 80 to 90%. I
mean,
yeah, I mean, like I especially like
debugging a test or like the CI thing is
bad. Like, I'm like I'm like, "Hey, you
know, you know how to write, you know,
print debug, whatever." Like, and that's
great. That's really freeing.
>> Digging into the problems that are
suitable for LLMs and the ones that are
not. Like, what what do you need to see
where you think, "Okay, I need to go in
and, you know, write it myself. What's
that 10% and also what's in that 80-90%?
>> Yeah, I mean, that's a good one. I think
about that. Yeah, cuz every time I sit
down, I'm like
like should I write this? I mean, the
answer's almost always no. Um
Uh
there's
things that are like lower level and
someone you know, so Codex the the
harness, the part that I you know, spend
my time on is in Rust. And that means
that you know, we can do and we do do
like operating system specific things in
that code base. Um
and actually and I spend a lot of time
on on the sandboxing, right? So, the
thing that really upholds like uh
you know, the security integrity of what
of what we're doing and the model can't
go outside um you know, the bounds that
you set. Um
you know, I I do more of that um by hand
because I need to make sure really sure
that that's all correct, right? That our
our test coverage is is good. Um
Or sometimes I'll you know, seed it and
then you know, once I've got like the
groundwork and like okay, I have the
pieces that I that I
was
had a lot of feelings about and then
could let like fill in the rest and that
sort of thing. But you know, a lot of
like refactors and things like that.
Actually, the thing like a lot right now
is like
you know, I have a build up a big you
know, PR that does too many things, but
I know it does too many things. So,
they're like okay, please you know,
please split this up into reviewable
sized commits. Um things like that. Like
I think about how much
time I probably spent on that sort of
stuff before and now I can relegate
pretty easily now.
>> Um what about um like code review? Is
there
like what percent of lines of code do
you
and at OpenAI generally are people
reviewing manually [snorts] or are there
agents that are like yeah, imagine you
write it fast or something. I don't
really need to review that. I mean
>> Yeah. I can mention it.
>> I would say I like the approach where
you know, the the agent should do
you know, multiple rounds of review or
whatever until it's confident and that
it that it's like I'm you know, worth a
human's time of looking at it. Um but we
still do look at it um like ultimately
before it goes in. I'd say generally
speaking. Um I think there's, you know,
we we have like our agents have the file
like everybody else does. They're still
sometimes you find like a gap in
knowledge that needs like that some
context that needs to get added back
into there or it's um
yeah, just just things that we haven't
yeah, memorialized that that the agent
knows but like as a human I I still
happen to know.
>> Right.
>> Um and things like that. So, we do catch
things. Um
but you know, I'll say actually now that
people are uh also using AI to write
their like pull request summaries. Um
our summaries across the team I'd say
are getting way better. So, now
[laughter] at least also when I'm going
into review, right? It's been reviewed
by Codex.
There's a summary that's like that we
actually make sure it has like the why
and the what of why, you know,
>> the reason behind the PR. So, that
>> is certainly I think helping like
get through these PRs faster, which is
good cuz there was a lot more
>> Yeah.
>> review to do.
>> That's I mean that's amazing. I feel
like
um 50% of diffs have like, you know,
almost blank and then the test plan
says, you know,
uh I don't know, arc build or whatever
the command is.
>> [laughter]
>> Um I want to talk about the the the
Codex CLI that's that's open source. Why
is it open source?
>> You know, for something that's that
critical to like what's going on on your
machine, right? Like that that like
that's one of the aspects of open source
is that I'm not you know, the most um
zealous about this sort of thing but I
but I I sympathize with it. This idea
that like, "Hey,
you're going to put this thing on my
machine.
I care about what it's doing, right? And
I think in this domain in particular,
it's really important that people can
look at it, you know, and have have an
idea of what it's doing. Um because you
know, people have a lot of questions
about AI agents and that sort of thing.
Um and so I think
I think this this
this area, this domain, I think it's
actually really important.
Um and also we um you know, we have
gotten a lot of uh I think like great
contributions about reports and things
like that that we um would have missed
out on.
Um and and and then also I think it's,
you know, um just
you know, sharing with the world with
like how this is done. Um so we do it
through code, right? I've I've put out
um one blog post about how the agent
loop works. Like there is a plan to do
more of that. I'm actually excited to.
It's just, you know, just it's just
time. Is is the limiting factor. So it's
really not
Yeah, it
was funny cuz I had I had two candidates
who came through and one's like he's
like, "AI wrote it, right?" I was like,
"No, no, I I [snorts] wrote it." And
another person came in and was like,
"Oh, you can tell that that, you know,
that you did not outsource the Okay,
good. Right. I was like, "Oh, thank you,
you know."
So yeah.
>> You mentioned the blog post. How does
Codex find what is available to it in
its environment? I when I'm running
these things, I'll see
it it's kind of amazing. It's thinking
to itself and like discovering all these
things in in my
uh terminal. So yeah, how does that
typically work?
>> Yeah, I mean there's you know, there's a
few. I mean there there's obviously what
is you know, when Codex is base training
like it loves to use rip grep, but it
uses rip grep very well to find all
sorts of things. Um and then there's,
you know, if you have your agent's MD
file and you say, "Hey, in this repo
like these tools are really important,
right? You should use these, right? Here
are the readmes or whatever." Um
or uh obviously if you use MCP and you
associate these MCP servers with your um
you know, where you're working on,
right? That that that um injects the set
of tool definitions like at the start of
the the conversation, right? So then uh
I kind of yeah, so that's that's not
even like discovery on Codex's part,
right? It's kind of just like put it
front and center there.
>> I see. So some of it's the harness
explicitly throwing that into the
context. And then there is a big chunk
though where the model is just doing all
the heavy lifting of finding things, is
that right?
>> Yeah.
>> Kind of like reflecting over your
career, the breadth and depth of your
work, if we look all across all of it. I
mean, it's it's insane. You were you
JavaScript front end, then you have all
these dev tools, you know, build, fuzzy
file search, you know, virtual, now
you're working on Codex.
You I'm sure you had to uh continue your
engineering educa- education to kind of
get through all these projects. What are
the top technical books that have helped
you educate yourself?
>> Yeah, I mean,
um
you know, so one was this uh this book
on operating systems. Um, it's like a
thousand pages or something like this.
Uh, it's the Addison-Wesley book,
primarily author, but it was funny
because I was when I was working on the
virtual file system. So I actually
gotten to that point in my career
without ever writing C. Like undergrad,
like it was like more theoretical, like
we we didn't just never had to touch it.
And then yet I'm like working on a
virtual file system project. And that
was like very low operating system,
that's why I was, you know, joke that I
was the kind of the worst engineer of
the project. And you know, and someone
said something and I realized I was
like, I don't know what they're talking
about. This is kind of embarrassing. And
I was just like, you know, what book do
I have to read? And I think my manager
Aaron Kushner at the time was like he
was like, well, there's this
thousand-page book. And I was like,
done. So I bought it. Read the thing
cover to cover, I like took it to Hawaii
with me, I took it everywhere until I
finished it. It's it's kind of amazing
and sad or weird like how um
how far many of us can get like in
software engineering without really
having a clue how computers work. Like
there's just so many of those
levels of abstraction.
Um but you know, on one hand it's very
freeing and then on the other hand it's
a little bananas. And I think that um
what I would say to people right now is
um
is you know,
actively trying to go like deeper
through the layers and understand these
things. Um
and uh
like
cuz many times
I saw other people do it and now I can
do it. Is that there are problems some
other people could solve that I couldn't
solve because I just didn't know that
like there was this cruft between these
two layers and if you got rid of it
right here you get like a 10x
improvement or something like that,
right? If you if you're just operating
so high up you don't really know, you
know, what you can what you can break
down.
Um
you know, so that um and so in terms of
books like uh I've enjoyed the like the
O'Reilly uh the Rust books. Um I I you
know, I'm a big fan of Rust. Um I think
that but they're also like well-written
um and and thorough. And then honestly
another thing I've been telling people
um that's not in the book category but
probably more fun and I learned a lot uh
actually um are um
these CTFs or like uh capture the flag
like security type competitions. And
just you know, it helps with like kind
of like adversarial mindset. It helps
with I think uh they're usually just
like it's like a it's like a decathlon
like a computer decathlon I feel like,
right? Cuz like like you they'll give
you multiple challenges and maybe this
one you need to like understand assembly
and this one you need to understand like
what someone's like janky PHP admin
pages do banging and all that sort of
thing. And it and it just forces this um
breadth on you uh in a way that's kind
of hard to
to generate otherwise. And it's also you
know, it's just more fun cuz it's like a
game and that sort of thing.
>> Can you give some context on what CTF
is?
>> Yeah, so it's it's uh it can be a number
of things, but uh it's it's usually a
competition usually in like the infosec
the security domain. And there'll be a
set of there's like the Jeopardy style
one which is like there's a bunch of
challenges. Um and like you know
designed like crafted ahead of time and
they all have point values associated
with them. And so you know there's
usually some fixed around the time and
it could be individual it could be with
a team and you're trying to solve these
things and and there's a flag there's
always like a secret you know um
piece of text
in there that usually has some format.
And the way is that you basically if you
can discover the secret piece of text
that means that you have
the the challenge is set up that you
would only have gotten that if you had
figured out you know reverse engineered
or whatever you were supposed to do and
then you get submit that piece of text
and that's your you know token to
demonstrate that you have solved the
challenge and so it could be like a race
to like solve everything first or get
the most points in a certain amount of
time or different things like that. So
it's like it's kind of like an escape
>> room but in your terminal
>> Yes.
>> only computers to figure everything out.
>> I see okay and your recommendation is
people who want to become better
engineers they should invest in doing
some of these CTF because they make you
solve problems that make you a better
engineer.
>> Yeah and you know and you you know also
develop skills and things that you just
wouldn't have you know if you're just
like a you know writing react every day
like you're probably not going to like
open up GDB and like reverse a you know
a tic-tac-toe game like I did that
because of you know CTF challenge was to
do you know exactly that.
>> Right.
>> Um and but then it's like but then I
learned how to use GDB and like and and
then then you start you know when you're
faced with other problems you're like oh
my my just toolkit of of ways to solve
things is just much broader now.
>> A lot of people especially earlier in
their career they see the power of code
X doing everything for them in the
terminal and I used to imagine them
saying, "Oh, well, I don't need to learn
GDB cuz
uh Codex knows it." So,
um what What would your advice be given
the landscape of these AI tools for
people thinking about their engineering
education?
>> Yeah, I know. That's I mean, I think
everyone's like struggling to answer
that uh question right now. Um
I do think about it, you know, a a lot.
I I I don't have a great answer. I I I
kind of personally come back to him. I
think about like
um
I still think like trying to forcefully
kind of go through the levels of of
abstraction and just understand um
you know, more like at a deeper level
how things work um is going to be
important. I mean, I think
this will change. I'm sure this will
change over time. But right now, it's
still kind of like
you know, you the questions that you ask
the agent is going to affect the quality
of the thing that you get out, right?
So, if you're not asking the right
questions, you're not maybe going to get
the best engineering solution out the
other side. You know,
as things go on, perhaps that will also
be,
you know, another layer that's removed.
I mean, I think, you know, that's
certainly where we're going. I don't
know on what time frame we'll get there.
Things do seem to be happening faster
than we expect. But, um
yeah, I I think in general, but
learning how to ask what the right
question is. And I And I haven't, you
know, for myself even like totally
pinned down what that means for for
somebody who's like starting out new,
right? I you know, fortunately I have
experience to to fall back on. Or like
that's where that that that taste or
that um
intuition of what to ask has as
developed. But, you know, if you're if
you're starting out, um
I'm still not sure yet. And it's also
hard to say because we we don't really
know 100% where everything's going.
>> Yeah, when you reflect over your career,
the expectations at these really high
levels is kind of crazy. I mean, it's
like already for most people this E7 or
senior staff level is this unattainable
level of impact. So, someone who gets
promoted to that level is thinking
I got to really work super hard now
because the bar is like up here. And
then you went two levels past that. And
so,
I have I'm curious like in the
day-to-day now, what what are your
thoughts on these like crazy
expectations? Is it stressful for you?
>> I mean, it never it was never not
stressful, I think. Um
for me. Because I really I think also
because I sat in calibrations, right?
And I um you know, so so for a bunch of
other people, you know, you talk about
their level, you talk about their
impact, and you you want it to be really
fair and have this integrity around
well, this level means this thing and
this is the impact of like that's what
it means tall is, that's what it means
seats is. And then knowing that like
then you're you're playing it out in
your mind like, well, someone's sitting
in my calibration and talking about this
thing and they want to be fair, right?
And I and it is a little scary like you
know, you get to E8 and you're like, oh
you know, it's a D1 or a director.
>> Right.
>> And you're like, how do I have as much
impact as a person who has maybe like
over 100 people
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> in their org. And so, that's hard. A lot
of people do it Again, a lot of people
who are are in IC who do it, do it more
by
uh
a different form of people management,
right? Where they're trying to you know,
like write the right doc and get the
people aligned and do that sort of
thing. And there And the reason that
they
do it and are not a director is that
often times the the people I've talked
to people who were in this like that
they're like, well, I have this
technical credibility or because I built
this thing like when I go to the team
and talk to them, it lands differently
than if like a engineering director does
or
some version of that, right? Happens a
lot. Um
And so then, you know, when you when you
say you're influencing, you know, 50 to
100 people as a senior IC, then you're
like, oh, okay, that's like, you know,
D1 impact. Um
you know, whereas as if you're a coder,
I see.
Um
Uh yeah, I
you know, being really thoughtful about
the projects that you pick. And it can't
just be like this is fun for me type of
project. I mean, you know, if you
actually care about, you know, not
getting fired or getting or you're
getting like same as me at all or or
better. Um
and even when I would start a project,
it's certainly like the later I went on,
I would think a lot about like, "Okay,
like I maybe there's this feature I just
want to write it cuz it's fun." I'd be
like, "Ah, no, I should let somebody
else do that and think about, "Okay,
I mean, it's kind of like with with with
codex now, like what code do I should I
personally write to maximize my impact
versus if someone else could do it about
as well as me, let's say 80% as good, I
should probably let, you know, have
someone else do that.
Um
and but but even then,
you know, if you're leading a
five-person project,
is that still you know, still getting
E8, E9 impact, still hard. Um
so
really finding that that uh project
that's a force multiplier. So, you know,
like like uh like the virtual file
system was a really great project
because that was going to
you know, we knew that down the road
like this was really going to unlock so
many things, prevent us from from being
completely blocked, right? Um actually
another big part of it is um and you
know, through one of my managers talked
to me about it is um
you know, not actually recognizing
senior managers enough who are the
person who um
pairs the senior IC with the right
project.
And uh cuz some
senior engineers are amazing
you know, fixtures slash coders,
but they're not the idea come up with up
with. And
they're the but they're the person you
want for like, you know, very difficult
um technical projects. I don't want to
out anybody in this. But I have people
in mind. And uh but but you know, a lot
of times it's the manager who realizes
like oh, this project needs this person,
right? And like that person would have
never realized it themselves.
>> One of your old colleagues at our verse
day thing I asked him you what are some
other engineers that you admire why and
you know, he came out and said your name
of course and specifically he talked
about your ability to start projects was
really good. And obviously I mean
look at all these projects, right? I
mean a lot of them you created them out
of nowhere. Like there was just you had
an idea and you went off and built a
prototype. You came back and you were
very convincing that it was a better
solution. Do you have any advice for
engineers who they have a problem with a
solution and they want to like build a
project from scratch?
>> I mean I think it I don't know a lot of
good projects I think come from being a
little bit dissatisfied about about
something, right? And I think um you
know, it's funny like sometimes I
for better or worse I was just so
charging ahead and just like building
the thing that like not really thinking
about um
like what the best way to do it was. So
actually a really funny example is um
Google Calendar. It was like going back
really far. I was like I want weather. I
want to have weather. All the little
icons showing the weather in Google
Calendar and I was like I'm going to do
it, you know, and I had mostly been
JavaScript especially and not done any
of the back end stuff. And I just like
charged through and I cobbled things
together.
And you know, made it happen and then my
tech lead was like wait, how are you
um
how are you storing that information
about like the weather and stuff? And I
was like
oh, I I just like you know, threw a blob
of like XML and everything.
Like that. He's like
he's like we should have talked about
protocol buffers, right?
I was like you know, like binary formats
to save bytes that I like I was just so
you know,
set on weather of all things that like I
never bothered to ask anybody if there
was like a better way to do what I was
doing. I was like it's done.
>> So I I mean, I guess that's uh
a unique skill of yours is the digging
into the satis- dissatisfaction and
solving your own problems. Seems like
almost every single one of these
projects is
I want my
I want something to happen. This this
shouldn't be this way. And then you went
and you solved it.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um Well, I think another unique thing
that I see is a lot of people they they
get to work and they I don't know.
They're they're in their dev
environment. I'm sure there were many
other people who saw with the Buck
story, for instance, they go, "Oh, wow,
this build is really slow."
Oh, well, like I I guess I'm going to go
to the micro kitchen and get your own
call its builds.
What gave you the confidence to know
that you could make it so much better?
>> I mean, that one was
you know, I I I have to credit like
having been a Google. I never worked on
the Blaze team. I never knew how that
like worked, ever touched their code or
anything. But, I was like, "I know that
there's a thing out there that has this
shape and is a lot better than this
thing." So, that's in existence proof.
Um
whether I could do it or not, like TBD,
right? But, I think that was helpful on
that one.
>> Yeah.
>> Um you know, I Yeah, I mean, there's a
lot of I guess prior art that gives me,
you know, confidence in things. And I
say And I you know, I usually generally
identify set myself as a coding machine.
I guess with Codex everyone's a coding
machine. But, um that, you know, I felt
that I was
had confidence like I could, you know,
build a prototype quickly, right? At
least answer that question. Or like the
basic my test my basic hypothesis like
spiritually should there be a way
forward to this thing that I think
should exist? And you know, generally I
could, you know, you're If you're
determined, you find a way.
>> Yeah, I've noticed that pattern. Um a
lot of people go to big companies, they
see this world-class infrastructure, and
then they go
to the other company, "Oh, you don't
have this? You don't have this?" And
they build their, you know, those new
versions of it.
I've read a lot of your writing at this
point. And it is so clear. It's some of
the best examples of good technical
writing. What advice would you have for
engineers who want to write better?
>> I mean, I think a lot of it is well, I
think reading other good writing is a is
a certainly good start, right? You start
to maybe, you know, consciously or
subconsciously start to pick up patterns
of like what what is out there.
I think um, you know, really
high-level thinking about like what
what what is it that I'm trying to
convey? What would someone actually
really want to know?
Um, and and outlining a lot up front,
right? Is I think a lot of people get
this feedback, but it's it's
it personal how really important that
is. And just being like,
does this set of things like linearly
follow? I think is a big thing. And and
and then asking yourself, oh, I went
from this point to this point, was that
too big of a jump? Is there something
that like somebody actually like would
have reasonably missed? And I think
uh
personally, I feel like that's I've a
I've reasonable feel for like what where
that gap would arise. And like and then
if you can kind of anticipate that and
magically put in the example that like
someone would have that someone needed
to make that jump. Um I think like that
at least for for technical writing is
like is is a big deal.
>> You have that career note that I love.
And at the at the beginning of it,
uh you lay out this three-step plan for
impact. Can you explain that three
three-step plan? Or like feel like
that's a good algorithm for people to
use in their careers.
>> Step one is uh figure out what you
really like to do, right? And you know,
as I mentioned like
>> [sighs]
>> it's good to broaden that, but it's also
good to to be honest with yourself or
say you don't know and like the the
quote the hero quest that I went on that
that didn't pan out because I I was
working on stuff that I didn't really,
you know, truly love.
Um,
and then two, step two was figuring out
what your employer is what's really
invaluable to them, right? And as I
talked about at Google, I I didn't do a
good job of that. I did stuff that I was
really excited about, but it wasn't you
know, it wasn't uh you know, AdWords for
Google or anything like that.
>> Um
And and then step three is like find
that intersection and then just really
lean into that. Um and you know, the
more that you can do that, I think the
more successful you're going to be. And
and and the And then the problem is
sometimes it's not always there, right?
And maybe you have to go, you know, find
somewhere else to make that happen.
>> Okay, and then yeah, last question for
you is
if you go back to yourself at the
beginning of your career knowing
everything you know now, what advice
would you give yourself?
>> I think I should have been
open to learning more things sooner. And
and I I you know,
to be a little gentle to myself and I
think other people are in that situation
is that
you know, there's so much to learn when
you're starting. And then whatever your
first programming language is, I think
it's funny. I think everyone has a soft
spot for it. They're like make excuses
for it. They're like ever like, "Oh,
it's No, it's a totally good language."
And I think it's because it's like the
first thing that enabled you to do a
thing, you know, do anything, right? And
and then it's like, "Ha, okay, I can
finally do something." It's such a
relief.
And um
And but it's also like a hazard because
like then you kind of want to hold on to
that thing cuz like you're finally
productive. And now you're like, "Ah, it
took so long to get to this foothold. I
don't know how long it's going to take
to get to the next foothold." So I think
like in you know, my particular case, I
probably did maybe went too deep with
JavaScript. And like like I said, it
took a long time before I wrote any C.
Um and I think uh
you know, as as if I I've been a little
bit more curious and a little more
flexible in terms of what like types of
projects I was willing to take on or
things I was willing to learn. You know,
it came eventually, but I think if
that is probably the biggest thing that
maybe could have made a shift for me
earlier.
>> Yeah, I I gather from your story there
was um
a point with the Xcode where you said
you you you hated Objective-C.
[laughter]
And then you you were you were coming up
with like ways to compile the
Objective-C into Java or Java into
Objective-C or something like that maybe
and then
you know, also talking about the C++ for
miles. It was like
it it seemed like a very concerted,
okay, I'm going to I'm going to learn
this as opposed to like just kind of
being open to it. So
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, makes sense. Well, maybe with
Codex in the future, it'll be less of a
hurdle for people. You could just kind
of say, "Hey, I know JavaScript, write
this in Rust or whatever." No, it's
true.
>> Opens a lot of doors.
>> For sure.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
your time, I really appreciate it. All
right, thank you, Ron.
>> Thank you for listening to the podcast.
It's a passion project of mine that I
really enjoyed building. Another passion
project that I've been working on kind
of in secret is building an ergonomic
keyboard that I wish existed and I
finally have a prototype, so I'd love to
show you what we've built. It's ultra
low profile and ergonomic and I couldn't
find anything like it on the market, so
that's why we built it. I'll put a link
to the keyboard in the description. You
can take a look and learn more about the
project there. We could definitely use
your support. Also, if you have any
feedback for me about the show, I'd love
to hear it. Comments on YouTube have led
to guests coming on like Ilya Grigoric
and David Fowler. I wasn't aware of them
until someone dropped a comment. Also,
feedback in the comments helped me learn
to reduce the number of cliffhangers in
the intros. So, your comments definitely
make a difference. Please keep letting
me know what you'd like to see more of
in the show and I'll see you in the next
episode.